<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analogue direction</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on analogue direction</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:05:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cheap Point n&#39; Shoots</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/pointnshoot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:05:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/pointnshoot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago when I was just getting into film photography, around 2017, I found a lot of YouTube videos about the Olympus XA. It&amp;rsquo;s a tiny point n&amp;rsquo; shoot featuring a rangefinder focus system. Great, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is its price. It&amp;rsquo;s been hyped up over the years and they&amp;rsquo;re now quite costly if you want one in good condition and working order &amp;mdash; and you do. Since they&amp;rsquo;re all electrical cameras, you can&amp;rsquo;t simply get them fixed if you receive a broken one or if it ends up breaking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago when I was just getting into film photography, around 2017, I found a lot of YouTube videos about the Olympus XA. It&amp;rsquo;s a tiny point n&amp;rsquo; shoot featuring a rangefinder focus system. Great, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is its price. It&amp;rsquo;s been hyped up over the years and they&amp;rsquo;re now quite costly if you want one in good condition and working order &amp;mdash; and you do. Since they&amp;rsquo;re all electrical cameras, you can&amp;rsquo;t simply get them fixed if you receive a broken one or if it ends up breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to go another route, instead buying the Olympus XA2 on eBay for about 22 euros. It&amp;rsquo;s a lot cheaper because they threw out the rangefinder in favour of a zone focus system and an f3.5 lens instead of the XA&amp;rsquo;s 2.8. To cut it short - I love it. It was my favourite point n&amp;rsquo; shoot, until I found the Minolta AF-C. Now things aren&amp;rsquo;t as clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After looking around for other cameras on the Swedish equivalent of eBay, I wound up purchasing a Minolta AF-C for about 100 Swedish crowns (roughly 10 dollars/euros). The Minolta AF-C sports an f2.8 lens and an early 80&amp;rsquo;s auto focus system. The point of this post is to compare these two fairly inexpensive point n&amp;rsquo; shoots to see what they have to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like with my previous (and first) post on this blog, I&amp;rsquo;d love it if you were to check out my photography work. You can find my portfolio &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kallmoraberget.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;olympus-xa2&#34;&gt;Olympus XA2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chose to begin with the Olympus XA2, as it&amp;rsquo;s the one I&amp;rsquo;ve had the longest and have the most experience with.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/olympusxa2.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Olympus XA2&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-and-functions&#34;&gt;Build and functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camera is very small, compact and made entirely out of plastic. However, it&amp;rsquo;s very dense and &amp;ldquo;built like a tank&amp;rdquo; despite its plastic build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything in the camera&amp;rsquo;s inner workings is entirely electronic and it&amp;rsquo;s therefore not possible to have it fixed if it were to break down. This is the reality for most point n&amp;rsquo; shoots, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underneath the camera, there&amp;rsquo;s a small lever with two settings &amp;mdash; battery check and self timer. It also works as a small stand for the camera when using the self timer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directly to the left of the lens is the focus slider. On this, you have three settings to choose between. Flower, person or mountain &amp;mdash; macro, normal portrait distance or infinity focus. My biggest gripe with this is that once you shut the clamshell, the focus returns to the middle option. If you&amp;rsquo;re out shooting and need to use the macro or the landscape focus distances and shut the camera, you have to remember to set the focus every time you open the clamshell up. This has cost me quite a few images as I always tend to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underneath the lens, when the clamshell is opened, is a small lever to set the ISO. It goes up to 800, so it&amp;rsquo;s possible to shoot slightly faster films. No DX coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lens--photos&#34;&gt;Lens &amp;amp; photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sports a 35mm f3.5 lens that&amp;rsquo;s, in my opinion at least, very very sharp. I&amp;rsquo;ll attach a photo below.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/street.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;A street in Uppsala, Sweden&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we look at a slightly zoomed in version of this photo, it&amp;rsquo;s very easy to make out the lettering on the sign that says &amp;ldquo;FRISÖR&amp;rdquo; in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/olympusxa2zoom.png&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;The very same street, zoomed in.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The only downside I can find to the lens is really the maximum aperture of f3.5. It can be a downside in darker environments. There is quite an easy remedy, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;darkness-capabilities&#34;&gt;Darkness capabilities&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/olympusxa2flash.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;The camera with the flash accessory.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you buy this camera, I would strongly advise you to get one with the screw-on flash attachment. There are two different ones &amp;mdash; the A11 and the A16. The A16 is stronger and recharges faster, but is also bigger. The A11 is the one that most usually comes bundled with the camera at auctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flash attachment makes it possible and easy to take photos in lower lit situations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/dinner.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Flash photo from a dinner party.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As seen in the photo above, it&amp;rsquo;s quite capable in dimly lit situations as long as the flash&amp;rsquo;s attached. The flash isn&amp;rsquo;t overbearing and renders quite good results. Granted, I&amp;rsquo;ve only shot black and white. I doubt it&amp;rsquo;d work as well for slide film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ISO going up to 800 you can shoot higher speed films and maybe, with a little bit of luck, get decent photos even in dimly lit situations. Most AF-C&amp;rsquo;s only come with a max ISO of 400, which makes the XA2 a clear winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One really good thing about it, however, is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t block you from taking photos if it deems the scene too dark. It lights up with a green LED to notify you that it&amp;rsquo;s too dark, but then it fires the shutter at the longest possible shutter speed and the largest possible aperture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ergonomics&#34;&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s small and comapct as can be. It may not be the most ergonomic camera in the world, but it&amp;rsquo;s also not bad in any way. You can open it and set any settings one handed when you get used to handling it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a small red touch button on the top right that acts as a shutter button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ease-of-use-and-quirks&#34;&gt;Ease of use and quirks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s very very easy to use. Apart from the focus, it&amp;rsquo;s an all automatic point n&amp;rsquo; shoot. Since the focus is divided up into three zones, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a brain surgeon to figure out what setting to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the quirks is most definitely what I mentioned earlier, how it resets the focus distance once you close the clamshell up. I fucking hate it. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost several good shots over the years by forgetting to set the focus again after closing it and opening it up again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;minolta-af-c&#34;&gt;Minolta AF-C&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve not owned the Minolta AF-C for as long, but I&amp;rsquo;ll do my best to give a short summary over its specifications, quirks and quality.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/minoltaafc.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;From the back&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-and-functions-1&#34;&gt;Build and functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the Olympys XA2, the Minolta AF-C is definitely &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; built like a tank. It feels significantly more plasticky and some parts of it can sometimes feel a bit loose and creaky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also unlike its counterpart, it&amp;rsquo;s not a clamshell design. It features a downward sliding door to protect the lens and the viewfinder. Unlike the XA2, the door feels very flimsy and the little &amp;ldquo;lens cap&amp;rdquo; that retracts when pulling it down has gotten stuck on me a few times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a very big advantage over the XA2 in its autofocus system. It uses an IR blaster and receiver in some very smart way to find its focus, which means it isn&amp;rsquo;t dependent on light as it instead works similarily to the bio sonar that bats use to navigate, but with IR light instead of echoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside comes at what speeds of film you can use. Just like the XA2, it lacks DX coding and you set the ISO manually on the front of the camera. There are two models of the AF-C. The most common one is capped at an ISO of 400, which means you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to shoot higher speed films and will also not be able to push regular films like HP5+. There is, however, another model of it that comes with an ISO-cap of 1000, a fairly odd number to cap it at, as there is no way to choose 800. I own one of each model and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend the ISO 400 to most people, as being able to shoot higher speeds is very important, at least for me. I always tend to push my film and shoot at higher speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lens--photos-1&#34;&gt;Lens &amp;amp; photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lens of the AF-C is quite capable. One thing that pulls it down, however, is that all my photos tend to come out slightly underexposed. I shot this roll at ISO 1000 and developed it as per ISO 800, but adjusted the time for the extra quarter of a stop.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/burgerking.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;A simple snapshot from when I got parked in by a truck.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we take a closer look at the photo, there is quite a lot of detail. The detail that&amp;rsquo;s missing is most likely from the push processing.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/minoltaafczoom.png&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Zoomed in version of the same photo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of complaints apart from the apparent dim exposures I got, but that could also be due to user error when correcting for the extra 200 ISO points between 800 and 1000. I have however heard from other people online that this is a &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; (in quotation marks as it can easily be adjusted for when developing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;darkness-capabilities-1&#34;&gt;Darkness capabilities&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/minoltaafcflash.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;With the flash accessory attached&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot to say, as I actually haven&amp;rsquo;t tested it out with the flash on. It does however have a flash accessory that just like the XA2 takes two double A batteries. Mine works and I&amp;rsquo;m sure it&amp;rsquo;s on par or at least somewhat on par with the XA2&amp;rsquo;s flash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a max ISO of 400, you won&amp;rsquo;t be doing much indoors or evening photography. Hence my recommendation to specifically look for an ISO 1000 model. Since it seems to underexpose most shots, most ISO 1000 shots come out as being metered for ISO 1200-1400 or so. This means that its low light capabilities actually extend quite far beyond the otherwise somewhat limiting max ISO of 1000. This also means that the ISO 400 version of the camera isn&amp;rsquo;t that far off from ISO 800 in real life use. You do however have to take this into account when developing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also holds the advantage of sporting an f2.8 lens as compared to the XA2&amp;rsquo;s f3.5 maximum aperture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ergonomics-1&#34;&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a bit bigger than the XA2, the ergonomics are automatically a bit better. Unlike the XA2&amp;rsquo;s touch button for the shutter, the AF-C sports an actual button that&amp;rsquo;s much more satisfying to click and also much easier to tell when the photo will actually be taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you hold the AF-C in the hand, the decent enough ergonomics are kind of overshadowed by the flimsy feel of it, though. The viewfinder is large and bright however, and features framelines to make composing easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ease-of-use-and-quirks-1&#34;&gt;Ease of use and quirks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s extremely easy to use. Being an all automatic camera with automatic exposure and autofocus, the only thing you need to set is the ISO. After that, you literally just point and shoot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you half press the shutter button, it locks the focus and a green LED lights up in the corner of the viewfinder. After that you can move the camera around and compose your shot with the focus set at whatever subject you&amp;rsquo;re shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two significant quirks. The first being the underexposure of most shots, which is easily fixed. The other is sadly that the light seals seem to be of quite bad quality. I brought the first AF-C I bought with me to Slovenia for a trip and when I got the scans back from the lab (I only do B/W at home), they all looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/gurman.png&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;A restaurant on the outskirts of Ljubljana, covered in light leaks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bought two working AF-C&amp;rsquo;s (I bought the ISO 400 version at first and then got my hands on the ISO 1000 model) and got two broken ones from a fellow analogue shooter. On top of this, I bought a data back for it on the Swedish equivalent to eBay. ONE, and I repeat, one (1) of these film doors had its light seals intact. The rest had light leaks. If you buy one, count on having to replace the light seals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re both very capable cameras. If I were to go for one of them, I have the most experience and feel the most at home with my Olympus XA2. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit smaller, the lens is amazing and it&amp;rsquo;s built like a tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don&amp;rsquo;t shy away from grabbing the Minolta AF-C, mostly due to the autofocus. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a few rolls through mine and I&amp;rsquo;ve only missed the focus once or twice. The autofocus system on it is truly excellent, and I&amp;rsquo;ve lost way more shots due to it resetting its focus every time you close it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d honestly give these two cameras a draw. They&amp;rsquo;re both EXCELLENT choices for cheap point n&amp;rsquo; shoots, but for the novice I&amp;rsquo;d stay away from the Minolta AF-C due to its bad light seals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-shots&#34;&gt;Sample shots&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll end the review with a few more sample shots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-xa2&#34;&gt;The XA2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the AF-C, where I haven&amp;rsquo;t had proper experience with the flash, the XA2 has served me with its flash for dimly lit dinners and parties.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/pouring.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Pouring up drinks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/sombrero.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Man in sombrero&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/threefriends.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Three friends&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-af-c&#34;&gt;The AF-C&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the AF-C shots I have at hand are all taken in regular everyday situations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/house.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;A house I passed by, taken in portrait mode and then cropped&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/dogsleep.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My dog taking a nap&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/dogplay.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My dog playing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/pointnshoot/volvo.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My car&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Film Photography on the Cheap</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/onthecheap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 15:05:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/onthecheap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-----whats-going-on&#34;&gt;So &amp;mdash; what&amp;rsquo;s going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it short, Kodak is increasing the prices of their films once again. Most price increases will be around the 10% mark, but some unfortunate ones, such as Kodak Gold, will go up by a whopping 30%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-of-price-increases&#34;&gt;Implications of price increases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NmzhsnUMwrQ&#34;&gt;Overexposed&amp;rsquo;s video&lt;/a&gt; on this. He ended it with a small rant about how these constant increases in price will essentially kill film photography. When YouTubers hype cameras up, their prices skyrocket. Kodak raises the price yearly, way above the rate of inflation. Even the hemicals are getting more expensive. Film photographers just can&amp;rsquo;t catch a break.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-----whats-going-on&#34;&gt;So &amp;mdash; what&amp;rsquo;s going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it short, Kodak is increasing the prices of their films once again. Most price increases will be around the 10% mark, but some unfortunate ones, such as Kodak Gold, will go up by a whopping 30%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-of-price-increases&#34;&gt;Implications of price increases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NmzhsnUMwrQ&#34;&gt;Overexposed&amp;rsquo;s video&lt;/a&gt; on this. He ended it with a small rant about how these constant increases in price will essentially kill film photography. When YouTubers hype cameras up, their prices skyrocket. Kodak raises the price yearly, way above the rate of inflation. Even the hemicals are getting more expensive. Film photographers just can&amp;rsquo;t catch a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one question remains, then &amp;mdash; how do I keep shooting film without getting ruined?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-a-few-things-clear-for-dumb-americans&#34;&gt;Making a few things clear (for dumb Americans)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m European. My country, Sweden, never signed some document about the euro and we ended up just keeping the Swedish crown as our currency. I will be discussing prices in this post in euros. If you need to check the difference between dollars and euros, just google it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that it might be possible to get stuff for even cheaper in the US or other parts of the world. Or that the tips I leave in the post may cost more in the US than in Europe (Foma products for example).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is also meant for someone that isn&amp;rsquo;t already well versed in the world of film photography. This is to be seen as a guide for total noobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;its-black-and-white&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s black and white&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start shooting black and white. B/W photography is what will get you into the darkroom for real and actually do your own prints. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to handle in all ways compared to colour negatives and it&amp;rsquo;s hell of a lot cheaper. If you want to get into cheap photography, you have no choice. Unless you bulk roll cinema film, but we&amp;rsquo;ll touch more on that later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and one last thing. You need to develop your film yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, onto the steps!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-steps&#34;&gt;The steps!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-1---bulk-roll&#34;&gt;Step 1 - Bulk roll&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/bulk.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bulk rolling means that you buy a long, usually 30m, spool of film. You then, in complete darkness, load it into a little machine that enables you to load empty film cassettes with film from the spool, all in complete daylight!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, you need to buy the film and the machine, of course. But you also need a pair of scissors, empty film cassettes and some strong tape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can buy already empty cassettes on most welk stocked shops for analogue photography, or ask your local lab if they have old film cassettes that they haven&amp;rsquo;t opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the price? Let&amp;rsquo;s start with Ilford HP5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;roll of Ilford HP5&lt;/strong&gt; costs &lt;strong&gt;9 euros&lt;/strong&gt; at fotoimpex as of writing this post.&lt;br&gt;
A &lt;strong&gt;30m bulk roll of HP5&lt;/strong&gt; costs &lt;strong&gt;130 euros&lt;/strong&gt; at fotoimpex as of writing this post post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 30m bulk roll is split up into roughly 18 rolls. So 130 euros divided by the 18 rolls means that you get €7,20 per roll, compared to €9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do the same comparsion for Fomapan, you end up saving more than half the cost. A 36 exposure roll of Foma400 costs about €5,50 whereas a bulk loaded roll of Foma400 ends up at €2,55&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-2---cheap-chemicals&#34;&gt;Step 2 - Cheap chemicals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having left the film itself behind, you also need to be able to get your hands on cheap chemicals. I would strongly advise any newcomer to buy Rodinal, Fomafix and Kodak Photo-flo.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/rodinal.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rodinal is a very very cheap one-shot (means you pour it out the sink when done) developer with an amazing shelf life. It&amp;rsquo;s said that they can be stored for up to 40 years without any problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having developed, you need a stop bath. Stop baths are actually just acidic solutions and nothing more. You can either add some &amp;ldquo;ättiksprit&amp;rdquo; as it&amp;rsquo;s called in Sweden to some water and be done with it. If you live somewhere where they don&amp;rsquo;t sell ättiksprit (vinegar essance according to Google), you can make an acidic stop bath out of regular tap water and a bunch of citric acid. Be on the lookout though, it can start to grow mold!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the fixer, I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with Fomafix, from the same people that made Fomapan. It has a shelf life of about a year and is very cheap per use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You only use about 2-3 drops of the Photo-flo per development. It will make sure your film dries well and doesn&amp;rsquo;t leave water stains. It&amp;rsquo;s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-3---diy-film-scanner&#34;&gt;Step 3 - DIY film scanner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, now you&amp;rsquo;re shot and developed your photos, but what are you going to do with them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best would of course be a darkroom where you can make analogue prints from all your photos. This will be quite expensive if you&amp;rsquo;re a total noob. If you&amp;rsquo;re serious about photography, I&amp;rsquo;m sure you already have a somewhat decent digital camera laying around that you used before getting into film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to use that to build this:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/scan.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the skeleton of an old enlarger I found at a thrift store for about €15. Onto it, I attached a €18 tripod head with a 1/4th inch bolt. I mount my camera onto the tripod head and I can then adjust all settings I need. The wheel on the right makes it possible to change the height of the camera to match your negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this, I also had to buy a macro lens that worked for my camera. I decided on an old Sigma lens for the Nikon mount (with an adapter ring for my Canon DSLR) that cost me about €80.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a bit more cost, I use the Lomography DigitaLIZA PLUS. It&amp;rsquo;s a small light table with holders for medium format, 127 and 35mm film. It&amp;rsquo;s built well and works wonderfully for scanning at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll add a few sample shots taken with bulk rolled film, developed in cheap chemicals and scanned with the DIY scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sample-shots----&#34;&gt;Sample shots &amp;mdash;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;taken-on-bulk-rolled-film-developed-in-cheap-chemicals-and-scanned-with-the-diy-scanner&#34;&gt;taken on bulk rolled film, developed in cheap chemicals and scanned with the DIY scanner&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/emohouse.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/militarylooking.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/circling.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/simon.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/pouring.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/onthecheap/snowhouse.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;This particular one is shot on medium format and therefore not bulk rolled. It it, however, shot on Fomapan 100 pushed to 400.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suzuki Press Van-120</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/suzukipressvan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 15:05:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/suzukipressvan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To introduce myself quickly, the name&amp;rsquo;s Erik and I&amp;rsquo;m into analogue photography. This will be the first post on this blog, hopefully of many. You can find my portfolio &lt;a href=&#34;https://kallmoraberget.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought the camera in question on eBay for about 260 euros. Finding one within Europe is very hard and I threw myself over the purchase button as quickly as I could. If you want to know more about the camera&amp;rsquo;s history and background, I strongly advise you to read Mike Eckman&amp;rsquo;s blog post about it, which you can find &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikeeckman.com/2021/08/suzuki-press-van-1953/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To introduce myself quickly, the name&amp;rsquo;s Erik and I&amp;rsquo;m into analogue photography. This will be the first post on this blog, hopefully of many. You can find my portfolio &lt;a href=&#34;https://kallmoraberget.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought the camera in question on eBay for about 260 euros. Finding one within Europe is very hard and I threw myself over the purchase button as quickly as I could. If you want to know more about the camera&amp;rsquo;s history and background, I strongly advise you to read Mike Eckman&amp;rsquo;s blog post about it, which you can find &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikeeckman.com/2021/08/suzuki-press-van-1953/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its name, it has nothing to do with the very famous company Suzuki, of which I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;re already aware. Maker or motorcycles and &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suzuki is a very common surname in Japan. The creator of this camera, Ryohei Suzuki, worked as a lens designer at what was then called Asahi. You probably know it as Pentax. When his idea of a medium format press camera didn&amp;rsquo;t spark their interest, he decided to start the Suzuki Optical Company which manufactured the Suzuki Press Van and the Press Van 120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said, I strongly advise you to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikeeckman.com/2021/08/suzuki-press-van-1953/&#34;&gt;Mike Eckman&amp;rsquo;s blog post&lt;/a&gt; about it. He and I don&amp;rsquo;t have the same version, as the camera was released in two different editions. The camera he reviewed was the original Suzuki Press Van whereas I&amp;rsquo;m in possession of the Suzuki Press Van-120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions&#34;&gt;Functions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &amp;mdash; onto the functions of the camera. Like I said, there were two renditions of the camera. The Press Van and the Press Van-120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;versions--format&#34;&gt;Versions &amp;amp; format&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several differences between the two versions, with the main one being the format. While both are medium format cameras, the original one featured an insert that allowed you to shoot 35mm as well as 6x6. The one I have, the Press Van-120, instead offers you 6x6 or 6x4,5. With the latter model they scrapped the idea of having a separate insert and instead provided built in flaps to allow for the 6x4,5 aspect ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original model also featured an automatic frame counter, which went out the window with the latter revision. In my model, you simply use the red window on the back.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/sidan.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;From the back&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be able to distinguish which format you&amp;rsquo;re shooting, you rotate the pressure plate when loading the film. Rotating it makes sure that you can only see one of the numbers through the red windows when advancing the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lens-aperture-and-shutter-speeds&#34;&gt;Lens, aperture and shutter speeds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;sharpness&#34;&gt;Sharpness&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipped with an Asahi Takumar lens, the shots taken with it are quite stunning and impressively sharp. If there was one thing I&amp;rsquo;d praise this camera for, it&amp;rsquo;s probably the sharpness of the lens. I can&amp;rsquo;t really see any degradation of sharpness around the corners of the image, or anywhere really. To be quite honest, it&amp;rsquo;s just an overall amazing lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 75mm, it&amp;rsquo;s on the wider end of the spectrum of &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; focal lengths. Perfect for what I had in mind when buying the camera &amp;mdash; having a medium format I can carry with me at all times and get most of what I want into the shot.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/sidebyside.png&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Show of sharpness.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h5 id=&#34;aperture&#34;&gt;Aperture&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lens starts at an aperture of an alright 3,5 and stops all the way down to 22. It remains sharp throughout the entire range. I have yet to figure out what its sharpest aperture is, as I tend to forget what settings I&amp;rsquo;ve used when shooting. One thing is clear however &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s easy to get that famed &amp;ldquo;medium format look&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/matildahjordis.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Medium format look.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very important feature is that the aperture &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo;, if you can call it that, clicks. This means you can use the camera in what is essentially shutter priority mode. The shutter dial spins freely, but if you have a set shutter and need to adjust the aperture, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to actually look at the front of the lens to adjust it if you get used to where the stops are or in what order they come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;shutter&#34;&gt;Shutter&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the lens itself is not only the aperture control but also the wheel for setting the shutter speed as well as cocking the Seiko-made shutter. It goes from one second down to 1/500 and features a bulb mode as well. My camera struggles with the two longest shutter speeds, but works more than fine on all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to having a leaf shutter, it&amp;rsquo;s very much possible to take images in lower light conditions, despite the lens only opening up to 3,5.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/blurrylowlight.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Slightly blurry but decent enough photo taken inside in a dimly lit room.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;viewfinder-rangefinder-and-focus&#34;&gt;Viewfinder, rangefinder and focus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably noticed, there are three small windows on the front. This usually means that there&amp;rsquo;s an uncoupled rangefinder. That&amp;rsquo;s not the case here, though. The rangefinder mechanism is coupled, but the rangefinder and the viewfinder are separated. This is apparently much like older Leica cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/viewfinder.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Rangefinder and viewfinder.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h5 id=&#34;rangefinder&#34;&gt;Rangefinder&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focusing is very easy due to the clear rangefinder patch, both in daylight and low-lit conditions. Being separated allows for the rangefinder to be very zoomed in which provides you with an unparalleled ease of focusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The view around the rangefinder is tinted slightly blue whereas the rangefinder patch itself is tinted slightly pink. This makes the focusing &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; easier than it otherwise would&amp;rsquo;ve been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;viewfinder&#34;&gt;Viewfinder&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only wish is that the viewfinder had been a bit larger, as framing can sometimes take a bit of concentration. Since the camera shoots two formats, the viewfinder is also equipped with a 4,5 mask on the sides. I think it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be kind of see-through. It&amp;rsquo;s yellowed with age on my camera and feels pretty pointless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;focus-dial&#34;&gt;Focus dial&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To turn the focus, you turn the dial on the top right of the camera. It&amp;rsquo;s sadly marked in feet instead of metres. The knob to the left is just a reminder wheel for you to remember what kind of film you&amp;rsquo;ve currently got rolled up inside. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually affect any settings.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/ovan.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;According to a video from Japan Vintage Camera on YouTube, a common problem with these is that the focus wheel gets stiff. Mine was when I bought it, but it was very easy to open it up and apply some lube to the mechanism. After I did, it&amp;rsquo;s very easy to focus. Zone focusing wouldn&amp;rsquo;t work very well for me, however, as I grew up with the metric system&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feel-and-subjective-opinions&#34;&gt;Feel and subjective opinions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be the most important feature, sometimes overlooked in reviews. In my opinion, this camera handles really well. Having to first check focus in one window to then move on the frame in another can be quite annoying, but you get used to it pretty quick. If something happens where you really need to get the shot, you can always snap away while looking through the rangefinder window. After having put a few rolls through it, you get fairly accustomed to the difference in framing between the two windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the controls on the front of the lens can also be quite frustrating, but having the aperture &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo; click is a very welcome feature. If the shutter speed could also click, I&amp;rsquo;d almost give it a full score. Not that I&amp;rsquo;m keeping one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest gripe with it is that it&amp;rsquo;s not a folder camera. It has bellows that extend, but the lens element and the controls do not fold. This limits my ability to keep it in my pocket out of fear that I might scratch the lens element or that the shutter or aperture lever might get stuck in a loose thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Suzuki Press Van-120 is overall an amazing camera. If I could do the purchase all over again, I&amp;rsquo;d probably pick a folder over it to be able to keep it in my pocket. Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve bought it? I&amp;rsquo;m more than satisfied with it, especially the amazing quality of the lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a short video showcasing the features of the camera. It&amp;rsquo;s just two minutes long and with no speech. It showcases all the features that the camera comes with.&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5oMx85JkKz8?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-shots&#34;&gt;Sample shots&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll end the review with a few more sample shots:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/gata.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;A man on the street I happened to pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/duett.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;An abandoned Volvo Duett&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/selfportrait.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;Self portrait in an elevator mirror&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/hus.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My neighbours house&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/dogoncar.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My dog sitting on the hood of my car&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/symaskinivar.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;My friend&#39;s sewing machine, an example of the low light capabilities&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/suzukipressvan/skiva.jpg&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 8px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;color: darkblue;&#34; &gt;An Ola Magnell record spinning&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The name&amp;rsquo;s Erik. I&amp;rsquo;m a 26 year old guy from Sweden who&amp;rsquo;s into analogue photography. My interest arose when I got handed my father&amp;rsquo;s old Nikon FE2 back in 2017 and subsequently started shooting film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like everyone else interested in analogue photography I&amp;rsquo;ve collected too many cameras over the few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been into the hobby. I created this blog as a way to write down my thoughts about the cameras I own and possibly a few ones I end up selling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The name&amp;rsquo;s Erik. I&amp;rsquo;m a 26 year old guy from Sweden who&amp;rsquo;s into analogue photography. My interest arose when I got handed my father&amp;rsquo;s old Nikon FE2 back in 2017 and subsequently started shooting film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like everyone else interested in analogue photography I&amp;rsquo;ve collected too many cameras over the few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been into the hobby. I created this blog as a way to write down my thoughts about the cameras I own and possibly a few ones I end up selling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my &lt;a href=&#34;https://kallmoraberget.com&#34;&gt;portfolio here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;quick-info&#34;&gt;Quick info.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Age &amp;mdash; 26 ( 1998 ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place of residence &amp;mdash; Uppsala, Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Favourite CRT TV &amp;mdash; Bang &amp;amp; Olufsen LX5500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Favourite camera &amp;mdash; Voigtländer Bessa R2 &amp;amp; Suzuki Press Van&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Favourite car &amp;mdash; Volvo 940.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Favourite music &amp;mdash; Hard to say. Probably Townes Van Zandt and Iris DeMent right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Favourite movie &amp;mdash; &lt;strong&gt;Highlander&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
